evening good evening and welcome i call to order this meeting of council for tuesday june 24th 2025. for all those able and willing please rise for the pledge of allegiance mr harris can you please call the royal members yes mr vice president mr men mr roya here mr
glees yeah miss craig here miss diaz here mr hirsch here and president beke council president
beke is excused for this evening a few friendly reminders please please note that this meeting is being live streamed and recorded if you are making a public comment this evening please do so at the microphone and state your name and address for the meeting record and also please be sure to silence any cell phones and or devices i'll first hear a motion for the approval of the june 10th 2025 minutes motion to approve motion in a second we have a motion in a second
mr harris mr mann mr arroyo aye mr cleese aye miss craig all right miss diaz hi mr hirsch
aye next we have proclamations honors awards and resolutions of recognition mr harris do we have any we do not mr vice president thank you mr harris next on the agenda is public comment this is reserved for citizens who have contacted the city clerk prior to the meeting to request the opportunity to address city council duration of comments are limited to three minutes mr harris
do we have any we do um tony dastra is our public commenter this evening tony dastra 700 block new
holland avenue i've come to say i don't feel this council cares about accessibility it cares about complacency and having an easy night it does not reduce the barrier to civic engagement here it maintains its hurdles heat waves like this week make it plain we need two-way online public comment at council meetings we had this technology during the pandemic we still have this technology what we don't have is the will no council member has yet the courage to advocate for it but maybe i can change someone's mind anyway back in december someone working very closely if not managing a campaign sent me a message that said you make yourself look like a fool by taking up literally everyone's time consider the fact this isn't the tony show and maybe you'd accomplish more by not being the center of attention that wasn't just rude it was meant to demotivate and silence me and frankly it reminded me of every time i've seen bullies try to keep people out of public spaces the same person later dismissed other residents concerns about policing with cyber marks here in council if that's who's advising your campaign then i have to ask is that the the kind of leadership you want to stand on the kind that ridicules public participation and defends the status quo I will not quietly email you all and beg for change this isn't a radical request it's common sense it's democratic it's accessible ironically the police often say in public engagement should be a two-way street isn't that funny City Council can't even model that transportation metaphor you wide in the road but not for safety not for equity you give the illusion of big action while steering back towards the status quo during the pandemic lancaster took a step forward you had to but as soon as the emergency ended you stepped back that is not leadership that is cowardice i appreciate your time to hear me but i don't owe you thanks for ignoring the second shift worker the single parent with two jobs the deaf who could use a chat box or even the elderly person who might be statistically more likely to die of heat stroke trying to get here walking here even if you want to be brave and become an example of change as opposed to an easy choice and bare minimums you know how to reach me thank you
thank you mr duster mr harris do we have any additional comments we do not mr vice president thank you mr harris next we'll uh move on to reports requested by council do we have any
we do first we have a presentation on research uh regarding single-use plastic bags
good evening good evening council my name is Molly Degger I'm one of the
deputy directors for the Department of Public Works I oversee the sustainability and environment division last month I was among several city representatives who had the pleasure of serving as judges at the school district of Lancaster's STEM fair we were inspired by the creativity and thoughtfulness of the students who were tasked with solving real-world environmental issues facing Lancaster City Isabel Keeler a student at Wharton Elementary prepared an impressive project urging the city to consider banning single-use plastic bags her work directly supports the community goals outlined in the city's comprehensive plan our future Lancaster specifically in system for growing greener which calls for reducing waste and protecting natural resources and system five building community and capacity which emphasizes the importance of environmental health and community engagement. Isabelle has been invited here this evening to briefly present her report to Council and I'm pleased to introduce her now.
I'm nine years old and I go to Wharton Elementary. My science fair project is that the City of Lancaster should ban single-use plastic bags. My research has found that there is three things that happen to plastic bags after we use them. We put them in water, which hurts the animals that live there. We burn them in fire, which releases toxins into the air that we breathe in. Or we bury them in the earth, which decomposes in 1,000 years. There's also some places that have already banned single-use plastic bags, like Lancaster Township in Philadelphia. I did the math, and by the time I graduate from McCaskey High School, people in the city of Lancaster will have used 188 million bags. My conclusion, people only use plastic bags for 12 minutes, but they last 1,000 years on the earth. If the city of Lancaster bans single-use plastic bags, it will be good for the environment and the people of Lancaster.
I think that deserves a round of applause. well thank you so much miss keeler for your advocacy and your presentation in front of city council uh very impressed that you're here at this age and advocating for a stronger future and a cleaner future for lancaster city so i really appreciate your presentation i will open it up for council if there are any questions or comments
counselor craig thank you isabel for your presentation that was most thoughtful thank
Thank you, Councillor Craig. Any additional comments or questions from council? If I may.
Councillor Diaz? No, go ahead.
Well, I have always been an advocate of plastic. I'm a scuba diver. So going scuba diving, the last thing I wanna see is our life animals that I would consider sea mammals, especially having that ingested in their bellies. So thank you so much for advocating. continue advocating get your friends together so we can stop making plastic because it's really
important for the environment as a whole thank you counselor diaz counselor thank you i just
wanted to echo everybody's uh statements excellent work miss keeler and i look forward to i was coming in here at the last minute but i look forward to looking at all the statistics you've
put together as well thank you thank you and i just wanted to say if there's anything that you'd like public works to look into and have any further discussions with council we'd be happy to do so thank you for the opportunity absolutely thank you mr harris yes mr vice president
our next presentation is regarding the capital budget and i think director campbell and director
campbell are both here to present the capital budget testing testing well thank you for
giving us some time this evening to talk about this this is the first official five-year capital improvement plan for the city of lancaster so we're going to take a few minutes to talk about just an overview and summary of the plan tonight so next slide please over the next few minutes we're going to address a few main topics first we'd like to review the difference between a capital improvement plan and a long-term capital plan we'll then show the total costs included in the capital improvement plan as well as funding sources for the plan
and i did send this out my apologies director campbell and council the presentation was sent out to full council earlier today if you want to pull it up on your devices sorry about that
director campbell no that's fine um so yeah we'll show total costs included in the plan as well as funding sources for the plan and then director campbell will talk about some key investment drivers in both a general fund and the enterprise funds for the plan um we're going to share highlights tonight and then a full list will be published and distributed before or by next monday June 30th and we'll review a schedule of the capital improvement plan process as well before we close just because this is the first time that we're doing doing this process like please so just a little review on what a capital improvement plan is last fall we spoke briefly about the difference between a long-term capital plan and a capital budget and a capital improvement plan so we wanted to just review all of these again this evening as we start this process officially so a long term capital plan is generally very long term meaning 20 to 30 years generally as you can imagine the further you get from the present time the less detail or exact specific pieces are available for projects so the long term capital plan generally holds projects that we know will be necessary during that time but sometimes doesn't include a budget as estimating for those projects can be really difficult that far into the future a capital improvement plan or CIP which will be referring to it as quite a bit as well a CIP pulls projects from the long-term capital plan that will be started and or completed in a shorter time frame which is generally five years these projects will include a budget for each project though again the further you get out into that five years the more estimates you'll see is we don't yet have have some specific numbers for some of those um the cip presented tonight is for five years so it's from 2026 to 2030. and a capital budget is pulled from the cip from the capital improvement plan the capital budget includes the project its estimated costs and the source of potential funding for the project so additionally a capital improvement plan and a capital budget the capital budget associated with it are different than an operating budget in that the projects very often continue from one year to the next until the project is completed so tonight we're going to give you a high level overview of the projects in the capital improvement plan from 20 from 2026 to 2030 the totals associated for the capital budget with that plan and then some of these projects included in the plan have already started but continue beyond the end of this year beyond the end of 2025 and some of the projects won't start until later in the plan some starting as late as 2030. so as i mentioned by next monday we'll publish the full capital improvement plan listing all of the projects and the budget for each broken down for each year from 2026 to 2030. and again i'll review the schedule for the process at the end of the of the presentation here all right so i'm going to start tonight with the total costs and the funding sources in the plan so there's 142 projects included in the plan for a total of approximately 299.1 million or about 300 million we have the projects in this chart divided into six different sections but three of the sections the parks the pw public works admin and the streets are all included in the general fund and then the other three sections sewer stormwater management and water are labeled based on the enterprise fund that they're associated with so the the colors are a little hard to see on this screen but the sewer is the orange and the water is the dark blue and you can see that those two sections have the biggest need they make up approximately two-thirds of the costs this is not unusual for water and sewer facilities since those utilities rely so heavily on major infrastructure to function properly however it does create some challenges as we've talked about already for containing debt debt payment costs and keeping fees reasonable as we try to ensure the systems are running well as well next slide please this is a quick breakdown of each of the funds the general fund and three of the enterprise funds as many of the counselors know that the city runs a fourth enterprise fund so the solid waste and recycling fund but because most of those services are contracted out capital costs and projects are not included in the capital improvement plan for that fund so it's just for the three enterprise funds and the general fund and you can see here the percentages of the total capital improvement plan for each of the funds next slide please so as I mentioned each project must identify a funding source or in many cases funding sources that can be used to ensure that the project is complete so here we've included 11 different funding sources in our in our CIP and our capital improvement plan though some of these are groupings rather than specific sources the committed grants one two and three those sources as an example are all of the grant funded funding that have been awarded so not pending grants but those that have been awarded but it's made up of many different individual grants so we have three different categories that are made up of many individual grants additionally we have an unfunded funding source that shows a need for funding this could be either grant or debt funding but that source has not yet been identified and and you will see in the plan that those are projects that are further out into the five years all right next slide please I thought it would be good to do a quick review of the funding options available to us to use for capital projects we talked through this slide it back in November but I thought it might be helpful to pull it out again so there's a there's a few main types but I'll talk about four different ones tonight there's two main types of debt that we pursue the first is a general obligation bond funding which is which is loan funding this funding must have a purpose described for it but it can be used for any purpose within our capital improvement plan as long as the description is included generally a project must be completed and the bond fund and the bond funds used within three years to be included in a general obligation bond if we maintain good financial health and therefore a good bond rating the interest rate on these this option is generally fairly reasonable though the the interest rate is subject to the economic and market conditions at the time penvest is another loan option for us this is our state revolving loan fund for utilities these funds would only be available available for certain water sewer or stormwater projects so generally they're not going to be available for any expenses in the general fund the projects for these loans basically need to be shovel ready meaning that the design has to be all done so while the interest rate is generally very good usually better than bonds sometimes the projects simply don't qualify for these funds or and must be funded through the general obligation bond or if we do feel like we can pursue a pen vest loan we may need to invest significantly in some pre-construction work before we can apply for the loan so that we have a chance of receiving the loan the third category grants are an option for some of our projects we work hard to get as many grants as we can for these projects but it isn't always a guarantee the projects must qualify for grant guidelines and often the grant process require requires almost a year wait to know if the funds are awarded or not so while we try this option as much as we can sometimes we aren't awarded the funds or as much as we're requesting, or we simply can't delay the project long enough for the grant timeline. Additionally, most grants do actually require some sort of matching funds from the grantee, so this means that the funds must be factored in from other funding sources, often in the form of bonds so that we can even apply for the grant. And then lastly, we didn't actually talk about this in November, but specifically for the sewer fund and you'll see this in the in the slides as well we generally receive a reimbursement from our partners of about half the cost of the projects because of the agreement that we have with them to provide services and infrastructure so it's only in the sewer fund but you will see that in the in the plan as well all right so I'm gonna break things down a little bit here so this is a breakdown of the funding sources with things grouped together a a bit more so these first three categories are the categories that we consider committed funding so funding that does not require further debt financing we currently have about 50 50.6 million in bond funding that's already confirmed that we're still spending on these projects we also have about 46.7 million in grants committed to the projects included in the capital improvement plan and then our sewer partners would contribute about 42.6 million for projects in the plan these three categories total 139.9 million or roughly 140 million of the funding for the plan so it's approximately 47 percent of the total plan and then the remaining 53 percent that 159 if you can go back to that slide sorry that 159.2 million that's on the bottom of the slide yeah That would need to be funded with either some sort of future debt or, as I mentioned, that unfunded category, which could be grant funding as well. Actually, I guess I should have just talked about that on the next slide, so you can go there. So breaking down that future debt a little bit more, I wanted to show just the maximum amounts based on each of the funds that we would be looking at over the next five years. This is assuming that all of the unfunded options at this point would result in debt, meaning that we wouldn't have any new grant funding. That's likely not the case, so these numbers could be lower as we receive more grant funds, but this would be the maximum amounts. And as you can see here, water and sewer do make up about 80% of the future financing needs. Again, this isn't unusual given their large infrastructure needs. And then before I turn it over to Steve, I just wanted to make a note about the total amount of projects that we have, so one more slide here. You can see the total amount listed here is 142, 39 in the general fund, 47 in sewer, 11 in stormwater, and 45 in water. And Steve's going to talk more about these projects.
Thank you for having us present the capital improvement plan. I'll be talking primarily about the key drivers of capital investments in the Department of Public Works. Now, the general fund, the next slide. Now, the general fund investments consist largely of work in the public right of way and construction and operations divisions. Public right of way includes parks, playgrounds, pools, et cetera, vision zero initiatives, active transportation slash bicycling infrastructure, and maintaining and upgrading the streets next slide the priorities that are driving investment in dpw's public right-of-way and engineering division include parks master plan the design and implementation of the first parks to be addressed from the parks master plan including south end joe jackson ewell gans and reservoir as well as next stages of south duke street mall and conestoga pines parks vision zero is largely represented by investment in the safe streets for all program and is based on crash data and the city's commitment to improving high crash intersections to reduce fatalities and serious accidents these projects will include church street improvements south duke street and south ann and judiata initiatives the active transportation plan adopted by city council in april of 2019 which is building our ever more robust bicycling network will include continued expansion of the network to be the most robust per capita in the region and for lancaster county to become a destination for bicycling examples of such work include the water street bike boulevard being done in conjunction with stormwater projects and a sewer separation the chesapeake and broad bike facilities working towards an inner bicycling loop so that ultimately residents from southwest and southeast lancaster can ride safely to the mccaskey campus and the northeast greenway walkway in conjunction with the eastbound connector phase two which further joins our active transportation network with the county's network maintaining and upgrading infrastructure including various traffic and pedestrian signaling efforts continued street lighting improvements and our successful self-performance of street paving projects rounds out the the maintenance and upgrading of infrastructure you can see that much of this work is ongoing baseline capital asset upgrades and other special projects such as parks transformations vision zero and active transportation are additional initiatives often supported by grants next slide the general fund also consists of work related to our construction and operations division upgrading and capital replacement of assets in our buildings and parks next slide the priorities that are driving investment in dpw's construction and operations division include maintaining our parks and public property the facilities portfolio we have 26 public parks and recreation areas five waiting pools at a one full-size pool eight major operational facilities ten public restrooms and we have conducted facility condition assessments as you know to be able to anticipate and properly budget for required periodical replacements and upgrades it also includes operational efficiency the recombination of facilities into centralized locations for efficiency economies of scale reduction of time and fuel use the consolidation of functions under fewer roofs for the archiving equipment and vehicle storage and warehousing functions and expanding our capacity and capabilities to increase revenue and reducing costs of our very popular and one of a kind in the county recycling operations it also includes the welcome center renovation which is the centralized hub for implementing the tourism master plan to highlight and serve lancaster as a tourist destination technology and advertising in conjunction with our key community partners will be part of that project as well next slide our green infrastructure and work to combine to combat combined sewer overflows for which the city is well known is critical to the capital plan next investment drivers in the stormwater sustainability and environment area include the following we're currently having we currently have 83 projects with nearly 400 public stormwater related assets most are performing well or outperforming and some of these are starting to need corrective actions. Regarding our long-term control plan, we have successfully persuaded EPA that we can maintain and thereby be certain of the level of performance of our green infrastructure. Green infrastructure is less expensive than gray infrastructure and provides quality of life benefits such as shade, reduction of heat island effect as well as stormwater management our legacy and portfolio of green infrastructure must be maintained to ensure performance and contribute to a lower overall cost to the long-term control plan with such success and affected of an effectiveness of this infrastructure we look for any new opportunities for green infrastructure whether in the public right of or in new or upgraded facilities this includes in conjunction with our paving plan GI corrective actions and opportunities at Reservoir Park and the operations center as well as continuing our trees for people program Lancaster's municipal climate action plan was adopted in 2018 and outlines a number of common-sense implementation strategies that will better position the city to lead our community through climate related challenges next slide with our municipally run utilities there are a number of investment drivers that affect wastewater including the advanced wastewater treatment plant shown here as well as the Susquehanna and Conestoga water treatment facilities next slide the investment drivers for wastewater include the upgrade and replacement of aging infrastructure such as piping and collection systems interceptors clarifiers a lot of these are technical things odor control systems and biofilter systems the healthiest part of the conestoga river outside of its origin near morgantown is just below the outfall from the wastewater treatment plant where we put cleaner treated water back into the river than we take out for drinking and with or without our consent decree there are ongoing wastewater investments required to meet standards in conjunction with the long-term control plan we have screening facilities pumping stations and chlorination infrastructure that continues to require upgrades and replacement any of you who have benefited from a tour of our wastewater facilities conducted by our deputy director for utilities christine volke hilditch can attest to the herculean task required to deliver epa compliant water back to the river in addition we are planning for a new anaerobic digester a very expensive proposition due to the limited and cons and constantly shrinking number of disposal sites for biosolids the ones that exist are very expensive many out of state, and with anticipated new regulations regarding PFAS in the sludge, unless we get ahead of it, our costs of biosolid disposal will absolutely skyrocket. Next slide. The investment drivers for water are even more extraordinary. In addition to similarly aging infrastructure, including the ongoing replacement of the very brittle transite piping, and a variety of projects related to water storage upgrades at oyster point reservoir and lafayette water tank pump stations replacement of ancient cast iron mains inside the city and upgrades of technology systems and the electrical equipment there's the continued investment in the large diameter water main that has been going on for several years to replace the existing large diameter main that is past its useful life the third phase of this work should be complete sometime during 2028 state and federal regulations require key large investments in two areas that you are familiar with because we've talked spoken about them in the past one is the lead service line replacement due to the lead and copper rule the work to be performed during the current five-year CIP will be to continue to identify lines continue to replace as we can and continue to seek funding for a major thrust in removal starting in year 2028 and then of course PFOS PFOA the firm forever chemicals although it is not clear what the future holds on the federal level at the state level the city may be required to remediate due to the drought of the last year thank heavens that's over we are teetering on the edge of compliance for the 14 parts per trillion state limits. We must propose a means of meeting the state standards and so we have maintained funds for study and design of remedies. Depending on what the state may require that we do, we may need to come back to this body for implementation funds. At the federal level, however, where compliance will likely remain at four parts per trillion rather than the 14 parts per trillion at the state level that is a virtually impossible standard to meet and should that be required of us we will definitely be coming back to this body these are extraordinary challenges but we are very pleased that we now have long-term capital planning tools to better anticipate and plan for how long for how these
investments get paid for i'm going to turn it back to tina i think we just have one more slide so i just wanted to talk through the schedule for the five-year capital improvement plan process this year the home rule charter states that we must present a capital budget each year by june 30th we're presenting this overview tonight and we'll have the details published by next monday as well as distributed to all of you once the capital budget is published there will also also be an option to submit questions online for the public through engage lancaster it will be the same format as what we're doing with the admin code and then on july 22nd which is a regular council meeting we'll hold the capital improvement plan and capital budget hearing which is similar to the operating budget hearing that we do generally in december so at that time director campbell and his team will share more of the project details in the published list and we'll share more of the breakdown of the cost details as well based on the published budget then on october 12th or sorry august 12th the first reading of the capital budget ordinance will happen at that council meeting and then the second reading of the capital budget ordinance will happen on september 9th our new home rule charter states that the capital budget must be approved by september 30th so that this timeline will allow that to happen welcome any questions thank you director campbell and director campbell
for the presentation uh very very helpful um just two questions that i have on my end can you clarify sewer partners is that other municipalities that are considered sewer customers
or is it yes we have we work with approximately eight to twelve other municipalities and for the the sewer lines that are outside of the city limits we work with those municipalities uh and they have a long-term agreement with us to partner to share uh the costs related to operations and and the uh uh capital investment that's required to service their sewer needs as well thank you and that and that represent as mentioned before that represents approximately 50
percent of the the sewer investments thank you uh and the second one is uh i guess each year when we're presenting the capital budget to council is that at that point in time will council be um given a progress report on what projects are happening throughout the year or have been done is that at the point in time when we can expect that yes and hopefully we'll be giving those
kinds of periodic uh updates on a regular basis possibly two to four times of course over the course of the year so that you will always be up to date. One of the things that I think is transformative for all of us is that we now have a means of reporting this information in a much cleaner manner and in a way that allows us to use it as a planning tool, and that allows us also to report more easily as well. So you should be able to stay apprised of what the expenditures are, what the costs what are the anticipated challenges to meeting those kinds of budgets thank you and just lastly
thank you to both of you and your teams for putting this together i know thinking this long term in advance is uh not only a heavy lift but also rare in municipalities so we're very lucky to have strong teams here in the city of lancaster that are this forward thinking and making sure that we're planning this far ahead so thank you any questions or comments from council
counselor craig thank you council um i think i already know the answer to this but the future debt planning of 159.2 million although that's in the future there is a possibility that we could
still get grant funding for that correct yeah some of it could be grant funding yeah i wanted
to make sure i understood it correct counselor diaz um mr campbell looking at the um the season
currently would you say that we're not having a drought right now because it's been raining so
dramatically like every weekend yes we are not having a drought right now we are officially out of the conserved water requirements we actually made an announcement to that effect about seven to ten days ago which is a huge relief on all of our parts it allows us to now test the quality of of the water upstream of the water treatment plant to confirm whether there's sufficient water in the river to dilute the PFAS and forever chemicals to be within the limits that we're looking for. We're required within an annualized basis to stay within that 14 parts per trillion. Like I say, we're teetering on the edge right now because we had two or three quarters where we were in full drought meant meaning that there was significantly less water coming down the uh down the conestoga river and yet the fur for chemicals were still there but now that we're out of that drought and there's a lot more water coming down fingers crossed our next testings will allow us to stay on the edge which just imposes us a lower level of compliance for from the state thank you mr campbell um mrs campbell
in regards to um the grants have you have we received any additional objections or denials from the federal government at all because i know that there's a a lot of things that have been cut but i wasn't sure if we might have received anything additional
thankfully no um we have all of the grants actually even a couple of the grants that we were worried about um are still continuing to go through for us at this point so we're grateful for
that okay thank you very much that's all i have thank you councillor diaz any other questions or
comments from council councillor ahmed uh thank you council royal and thank you to both director campbell's i really appreciate the forward thinking of this capital plan um my question is regarding the 2028 bond if we are unable to secure the other 29 million what would be the feasibility of obtaining the whole 51 million through that bond yeah i mean that would
definitely be a possibility this would be you'll you'll see because we'll be looking at this each year you will start to see those 2028 bonds get a little bit more fleshed out as we get into next
year um and in 2027 as well thank you and my my second question was regarding the other financing given some of the preventative maintenance that we'll do and you know investments in green infrastructure could we see the total projected funds needed could this be reduced in any way
without doing deferred maintenance you want to answer that that's a very dangerous question
that you're asking we as a city of lancaster already take very good care of the infrastructure that we currently have i did we've identified certainly within the stormwater infrastructure that in order to be able to utilize it as a tool for reducing the requirements of the consent decree we need to make sure that we are maintaining that green infrastructure at a level that is predictably performing at levels that we can pre that we can predict um we're for the last 15 to 25 years we've been replacing old infrastructure slowly but surely replacing transit lines for the last 10 to 15 years we've also been replacing lead service lines previous to the lead and copper rule however there's a lot of old infrastructure some of it as much as almost 200 years old that often needs to be replaced never mind the fact that there's the the large diameter pipe which is large largely made of steel and it has ex it has exceeded its useful life several years ago so we're we are continuing to make those replacements for for its benefit having said all of that we predictably without unfunded mandate requirements we are probably in a very good position to continue to manage and maintain the infrastructure that we currently have the big monkey wrench that gets thrown into the works is having to deal with these unfunded mandates the lead service line replacements on an incredibly short timeframe of approximately 10 years to replace rather than what originally had been asked for, which was 30 years, is what may make the cost of doing the lead service lines very difficult to reach. And that's one of the reasons why we worked so hard to work with the public to self-identify these lines so that we had a better sense going before the deadlines of what the likely amount of lead service lines to be replaced will be. We still don't know that full number. We're about to get new information from what we call machine learning over the course of the next several months, which hopefully will drastically reduce that amount. But we have to be conservative and figure that any line, and in fact the feds tell us, line that is not already identified as lead or is not lead must be assumed to be lead. So the more we identify the lead lines and the ones that are not lead, the better we are financially. The last and most unpredictable and trickiest and most expensive of these costs is going to be dealing with PFAS, PFOA. Only about, I would say, 20 to 25 percent of the nation has PFOA challenges in the way that the old cities of the Northeast and old cities in the Midwest have. A lot of it is because we have PFOS, PFOS was used in fertilizers and in pesticides for a long time, much of that has been discontinued, however PFOS is still continued to be used in plastics in many of the fire reduction clothing and the chemicals that are used for other purposes. And the regulations are not imposing themselves on the source of PFAS. They're imposing themselves on the water system. 20% of the PFAS you are exposed to comes through the water systems. The rest of it does come through plastics, through the air, through soil, through other means of production, and you may actually have more access to PFAS if you drink your water through plastic water bottles all the time than using the water out of your tap. However, the regulations are very strong. The state of Pennsylvania up until now has had really good regulations, 14 parts per trillion has been one of the most aggressive of the standards of the states in the country and we have been able to stay within that limit except for periods of severe drought as we had over this last year. If the standard goes to four parts per trillion, then it really becomes an all bets are off situation where one has to look at extraordinarily expensive options and we would need to very strongly seek other kinds of funding and support we would need federal support we need all kinds of other ways of being able to take that on and what you'll see as we've talked about it in terms of the long-term control plan is we're also trying to space out the requested funding for the long-term for the consent decree initiatives so that it minimizes or does not overturn the apple cart in terms of how much it's going to cost over time to take care of these infrastructure matters. So the big items that are unpredictable are the lead service lines and the PFAS, PFOA. Other than that, we are generally in very good shape in terms of being able to manage infrastructure in a way that that can allow us to be much more predictable about the costs involved
can i just add briefly um two things one is this um tool that um steve mentioned earlier that we have now is is wonderful we've been very excited about it um but it's also helping us to prioritize projects so um i talked about this in the fall and we can talk more about it in july but we also focus on you know debt targets for debt repayment in our operating costs as well as targets for percentages of average household income for for fees that we're charging so we're looking at those as we were setting this up we needed to prioritize some things kind of out of the plan so that we could try to stay within some of those those limits and we'll continue to to do that the other thing i just wanted to mention is we have two pretty large projects that aren't connected with unfunded mandates but are really once-in-a-lifetime projects the water main the water transmission water main transmission it's a you know it's its life cycle is or its useful life is about 70 years but we have to to replace it now because it was it's more than 70 years old and and the anaerobic digester which that which Steve mentioned already is another one of those kind of once-in-a-lifetime things and unfortunately they're
they're happening now as well thank you that was very thorough and you kind of alluded to my final question with that additional 51.8 million what is the budgetary impact on you know future projections and was that included with
any financial outlooks yeah so that'll be included in the the 10-year outlooks that we show with the operating budget that's all included in that in those pieces thank you and i really appreciate
the presentation and that concludes my questions mr vice president thank you councillor mead
counselor craig thank you the water main you said it's it's seven the lifespan is seven years 70 70 years so how far over 70 are we i'm not wanting to scare anybody but we're we're a good
10 percent of its useful life over its anticipated useful life yeah it was built in the 1950s and had a it was expected to end its useful life in around 20 2010. thank you
And I ask that question because, you know, we need to know the gravity of what we're facing and how important it is to get these things addressed as fast as humanly possible, you know? So thank you.
Thank you as well for asking.
Any questions or comments from council? Well, thank you both for the presentation, and we'll look forward to the capital budget getting presented. Very good. Thank you. next we'll move on to interim reports of committees of council mr. Harris do we have any mr. Harris do we have any interim reports of thank you we move on to a legislative agenda and the first item is resolution and made administration resolution number 47 2025 mr. Harris a resolution the council of
the city of Lancaster approving the adoption of an amendment to the Act 537 official sewage facilities plan for the city of lancaster mention to approve second we have a
motion in a second i believe this is uh the first time this is uh appearing before council this amendment is similar to many that come before council ensuring that this project meets the requirements for sewage capacity and all the standards for our sewage module plans so director delves anything that i should be adding to this or oh okay perfect awesome good evening if you just want to click it one more time there you go should be good good yep okay lauren finn
senior planner uh city um this plan uh this sewer amendment is for 523 woodward street um this property is being subdivided um and so it's going from one parcel to three parcels and what the land developer is doing is adding on so it's a it's a group of row homes and the developer is adding on to the end and so redeveloping the end unit and then adding on two additional units and so the sewer capacity will go from having to serve one unit to having to serve three units i think that the the most interesting part of this land development just for your own knowledge is that it's a former rackel property and so it's nice to see that it's moving forward through land development and it's about to go to the planning commission probably pretty soon thank you for the
the context any questions or comments from counsel from the public thank you
mr. Harris mr. Mudd aye mr. Roya aye mr. Cleese aye miss Craig all right miss Diaz aye mr. Hirsch all right that concludes our
legislative agenda we'll move on to the second public comment period this is open for comment about issues that are not on the agenda and the duration of the comments is limited to three minutes any public comment
Yeah, these are more free-spoken comments. This weekend, I was driving for Uber. I understand this is more of a traffic commission thing, but I just want to say it publicly that we really should figure something out here. One of the weirdest nights I've had driving, some positive interaction, some negative. The positive interaction was somebody came down from Hershey because they heard about our nightlife and they loved it. uh so it's always good to have someone come down from another place and be like yeah it's cool here i love it great nightlife but the trade-off to that nightlife in my experience uber driving is parking and uh there's two locations i think we really need to grapple with a parking situation one being telus 360 on the weekends i think having those uh parking spaces in front of the bars free would be amazingly helpful to traffic flow and congestion at night, maybe reduce some conflicts, protect some pedestrians, and the other one, which is more close to home here, right outside of City Hall, it's really frustrating to me to see people park their cars not too far from parking garages with the intention to get drunk in the city of Lancaster and then pull off and drive away, especially in a no parking zone outside i think it's something we need to handle more seriously as a public as a government because at the end of the day i mean let's take all the drunk driving stuff aside we have parking garages for a reason we invest in this infrastructure for a reason and i do not like seeing people just look for free parking especially when they're going out to get have a a good time so yeah I would appreciate more attention to that maybe some things put together because it does need to change in ordinance like I said I understand this is a traffic Commission thing but I'm not gonna come on 3 30 on that day I am typically working so I'm sharing those concerns here and I hope you guys move on plastic bags sooner rather than later that's all I have
thank you any additional public comment I'll conclude our second public comment period next will be the report of the mayor we do not have any tonight move on to the report of president of council which we also do not have any and we'll move on to council comments I'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn second motion to adjourn in a second all those in favor aye motion adjourned or
meeting